<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title>lujji</title>
  <subtitle>embedded stuff</subtitle>
  <link href="/blog/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  
  <link href="http://lujji.github.io/blog/"/>
  <updated>2016-09-12T21:50:45.151Z</updated>
  <id>http://lujji.github.io/blog/</id>
  
  <author>
    <name>lujji</name>
    <email>lujji at protonmail com</email>
  </author>
  
  <generator uri="http://hexo.io/">Hexo</generator>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Adding Trace support to ST-LINK clones</title>
    <link href="http://lujji.github.io/blog/stlink-clone-trace/"/>
    <id>http://lujji.github.io/blog/stlink-clone-trace/</id>
    <published>2016-09-10T20:54:00.000Z</published>
    <updated>2016-09-12T21:50:45.151Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>When it comes to programming ST microcontrollers, I prefer to use Discovery boards (mainly because you can <a href="https://www.segger.com/jlink-st-link.html" target="_blank" rel="external">turn them into J-Link</a>). However, I got tired of carrying around the whole dev-board just for the programmer, so I ordered a cheap st-link clone due to it’s small form-factor.<br><a id="more"></a></p>
<h2 id="The-clone"><a href="#The-clone" class="headerlink" title="The clone"></a>The clone</h2><img src="/blog/stlink-clone-trace/st-link.jpg" alt="ST-Link clone" title="ST-Link clone">
<p>For less than 3$ you get a nice dongle in aluminium case and some wires. After taking a closer look I noticed that there is no <strong>SWO</strong> pin on the pinout. Perhaps SWIM pin would dual-function as SWO when working with STM32? Unfortunately this wasn’t the case. So what, does it mean I have to use another USB cable just for UART? No way, I’m not going back to the stone age, I want my Trace!</p>
<h2 id="Research"><a href="#Research" class="headerlink" title="Research"></a>Research</h2><p>Trace is a very neat feature. One of the common uses is redirecting <code>stdout</code> stream to stimulus port 0 in order to printf debugging information. All recent versions of ST-Link v2 support this feature, so the first thing I did was check if the dongle is running the original ST-Link firmware. I launched ST-LINK Utility and updated the firmware with no issues whatsoever. So now we know that the dongle is running the latest official firmware and supports trace functionality.</p>
<img src="/blog/stlink-clone-trace/schematic.png" alt="ST-Link schematic" title="ST-Link schematic">
<p>I couldn’t find schematics for a stand-alone programmer so I assumed it would be identical to the one present on Discovery board. PA10 is used for SWO so the next step would be pretty straight-forward.</p>
<h2 id="Modding"><a href="#Modding" class="headerlink" title="Modding"></a>Modding</h2><img src="/blog/stlink-clone-trace/st-link-mod.jpg" alt="5V pin converted into SWO" title="5V pin converted into SWO">
<p>I’ve cut the trace from 5V pin right after the via and soldered some bodge-wire to PA10 (pin 31). I also added a 22&#937; resistor in case something goes horribly wrong. Initially I wanted to use SWIM pin since I don’t care about STM8 and it would only require desoldering one resistor without cutting any traces, but the 5V pin was easier to reach.</p>
<p>Time for some testing.<br><img src="/blog/stlink-clone-trace/trace-screenshot.png" alt="" ""="" title=""></p>
<p>SWO Trace works perfectly fine which makes the dongle much more useful.</p>
]]></content>
    
    <summary type="html">
    
      &lt;p&gt;When it comes to programming ST microcontrollers, I prefer to use Discovery boards (mainly because you can &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.segger.com/jlink-st-link.html&quot;&gt;turn them into J-Link&lt;/a&gt;). However, I got tired of carrying around the whole dev-board just for the programmer, so I ordered a cheap st-link clone due to it’s small form-factor.&lt;br&gt;
    
    </summary>
    
    
      <category term="st-link" scheme="http://lujji.github.io/blog/tags/st-link/"/>
    
      <category term="stm32" scheme="http://lujji.github.io/blog/tags/stm32/"/>
    
      <category term="trace" scheme="http://lujji.github.io/blog/tags/trace/"/>
    
      <category term="swo" scheme="http://lujji.github.io/blog/tags/swo/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
</feed>
